this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet SC radio
brings to relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio was brought to you by I Triple
E software magazine online at computer
org slash software hello this Charles
Anderson for software engineering radio
today I'm talking to James Turnbull of
docker James
Turnbull is a free software and open
source author security specialist and
software developer he is currently the
vice president of services at docker he
has held similar roles at puppet labs
venmo he's written books on docker logs
- puppet Linux system administration and
security James is there anything else
you'd like to add no that I think that
pretty much covers it great well today I
will be talking to James about the
docker project James welcome to software
engineering radio thank you glad to be
here so we'll start out very high-level
briefly what is dr. so docker is a
container virtualization technology so
it's like a very lightweight virtual
machine and in addition to food in
containers we also provide what we call
a developer workflow which is really
about helping people build containers
and build applications inside containers
and then share those amongst their
teammates great
so what problems does it address so it's
a couple of problems we're looking at
specifically the first one is really
aimed at at the fact that the virtual
machine is is a fairly large weight
compute resource it's not know your
average virtual machine is a a copy of
an operating system running on top of a
hypervisor I run into off a physical
hardware which your application is then
on top of and that that presents some
challenges for you know speed and
performance and it presents some
challenges in a sort of more agile sort
of environment so we're aiming to solve
problem
producing a more lightweight a more
agile compute resource so one that most
docker containers launch in sub-second
and you can they don't have a hypervisor
they sit directly on top of the
operating system so you can pack a lot
of them onto a auto physical machine or
onto a virtual machine um so you get a
lot of scalability the second problem
we're trying to look at is that we
identified the fact that for most people
that the most important ITI set their
own is to sort of the code that they're
developing and that code lives on a
developer's workstation or laptop or on
a dev test environment and it's not
really valuable to the company until it
actually gets in front of a customer and
the process by which it gets in front of
a customer that sort of workflow of sort
of dev test staging deployment
production is one of the most friction
fall in nit and the whole DevOps
movement for example sort of emerged out
of the fact that but one of the classic
stumbling blocks in in a lot of
enterprises I tell them as actions a lot
of our children's agents will stop is
that you know developers build code and
applications they ship them to
operations people and operations people
discover those code and applications
don't run in production so the classic
you know works on my machine
you know operations problem now so we
were aiming to build a lightweight
compute technology to help people put
code and applications inside that
computer sources have them be portable
all the way through the dev test it and
then be able to be instantiated in
production having made the assumption
that what you build and run in dev test
looks the same as all your board and one
in production okay we'll get into some
some of the details later but what are
some good or typical use cases where a
developer or an admin might want to use
docker we have a couple of really hop
use cases right now the first one is
this sort of continuous integration
continuous deployment world docker being
so lightweight it means that we have a
lot of developers who build stacks of
document owners on their laptops that
replicate some sort of production
environments for example a lamp stack or
you know a multi-tier application they
can run a build their application
against that stack which means they're
pretty comfortable
what they're riding against probably
looks like production and when they
actually run tests so they build things
they are they or they you know do
acceptance testing that it actually
looks like production because you can
then move these containers around and
they're very portable it could be things
like let's say you have a Jenkins
continuous integration environment
instead of relying on virtual machines
we have to speed up in your virtual
machine you install the software install
your application source code then run
the tests and then Toby tear it all down
again because you may have destroyed the
the VMS on the test process and repeat
that cycle you know you may be a part of
your your CI build process let's say I
take ten minutes to build those virtual
machines in the docker world you can
build those virtual machines in a matter
of seconds or the containers that
replace them in a matter of seconds
which means if you've got ten minutes
out of your build your build build test
run
that's an amazing cost saving like if
you're just focused on on building you
know you build very quickly a couple of
containers and then run your tests and
then you get your test results you can
work out when you need to make some
changes we run the test process and
allows you to get much more bang out of
your buck from continuous deployment
continuous testing sort of model the
other area where we're seeing a lot of
interest in the moment is what we call
sort of high capacity where people
traditional virtual machines have a
hypervisor the hypervisor probably
occupies about 10 to 15 percent of the
of the capacity of our hosts and we have
a lot of customers for whom that ten to
fifteen percent is quite an expensive
kind of 15 percent and they want to say
okay let's let's rip that out and
replace it with the docker host and then
we can run lots more containers we can
run the hyper scale numbers of
containers on a host containers because
of that lack of a hypervisor and they
sit right on top of the operating system
I'm very very fast
IBM alyssum research last year that
suggested that your average container on
a per transaction basis is about twenty
six times faster than a virtual machine
which is pretty amazing Wow yeah that is
that is amazing so this doctor enables
faster development you were
agile and then when we get to operations
it allows us even greater density yeah
so let's kind of dive into a little bit
of the details about how docker does
what it does dr. is based on containers
and the containers provide an isolated
environment for user-mode code some of
our listeners may be familiar with
earlier container systems like Solaris
zones or FreeBSD jails or even going
back to the chroot system call from UNIX
version 7 the code executing in a
container is has its own isolated
filesystem and can only see processes in
the same container let's consider those
separately how does the container have
its own copy of the file system without
duplicating the space between identical
containers especially when you're
talking about hyper scale like that
sure so one of the other interesting
technologies that docker relies on is a
concept we call copy-on-write
and there's a lot of file systems that
provide the sort of capability and be
TFRs or bottle service and device mapper
has a function called thin provisioning
and another another operating system
file system called a ufs foot they all
have one thing in common which is that
it's a copy-on-write model which is sort
of what the kernel developers call a
union file system essentially what
happens is that you build layers of a
file system so every docker container or
is built on what we call an image the
docker image is like a pre-baked you
know a pre-baked file system that
basically contains a very thin layer of
of libs and binaries libraries and
binaries that are required to to talk to
to make your application work and
perhaps our application code and maybe
some supporting packages for example you
might have a lamp stack that might have
you know that a container that has a
patch unit and Lib C and about a very
small number a very thin shim that takes
out being an operating system that image
is saved in its own its own core
a layer a safar system layer if I was to
then make a change to that image I for
example I wanted to install another
package I'd say okay I want to have a
PHP as well so I say on an Apple 2
system I say apt-get install PHP and
what docker does is it's are you want to
create a new thing I'm going to create a
new layer on top of our existing layer
and I'm only gonna add in the things
that I've changed so I'm so for example
I'm gonna add in the new package and
that's either so this layered
construction means that now I end up
with a read-only sort of file system
contained on which has multiple layers
and so you can think about each layer a
bit like a git commit or a version the
troll commit and I can as a result I end
up with a very lightweight system that
only has the things on it that I want
and when I'm rebuilding things for
example that docker understands that I
can case things so it says ah you've
already installed PHP I'm not going to
make any changes to the environment
because I see that you've you know
you've you I'm not going to have to
write anything so I'm just gonna use
their existing layer and I'll drag that
in it's the PHP layer so for example
you're changing your source code instead
of a like a virtual machine you may be
rebuilding the virtual machine with
doctor you say ah here's the new commit
of my source code I mean I add it to my
docker image and maybe that's a you know
10 10 kilobytes or something like that
worth of code change
doctor says art that's the only thing
you want to change therefore that's the
only thing I'll write to the file system
as a result it's very lightweight really
really fast to build and with the case
extraordinarily fast to rebuild okay so
that the layers are a bit like snapshots
in a virtual machine but they are very
much like that except they're snap you
know they're they're probably a little
bit more flexible and they're more
because of though that's a read-only
nature you're not capturing the you know
a snapshot is is can be sometimes can be
if you have reapply a snapshot there's
no guarantee that the system will return
to its running state whereas this is
actually you know it's it's just the
binaries and libraries it's that it's
the file system rather than the in
memory state of things so if you think
about one of the
bosses to do this with this device
mapper and we use their thin
provisioning capability which was
originally designs the snapshotting tool
okay I also mentioned that a process in
a container can only see other processes
in the container explain how that works
sure so docker relies really have there
are two pieces of Linux kernel
technology the first one is called
namespaces and namespaces is essentially
what that Linux kernel does when you
work
so example if you run a new process on
linux kernel then you're basically
making a system call to the namespaces
that the name spec the process name
stage to say ah i won't create a new
process if you want to create a new
network interface you're making a call
to the network namespace and and the
curl assigns you a your own namespace
that has a process and it has whatever
other resources you want for example
might have some access to the network
might have access to some parts of the
filesystem you know i have access to
system memory or CPU we basically say to
when we created AA container we were
eight to make it a bunch of calls to the
linux kernel to say can you build me a
box and the box should have access to
this particular file system access to
cpu and memory access to the network and
should should be inside this process
namespace and from inside that process
namespace you're quite right you can't
see any other process namespaces outside
the second piece of technology we use is
called control groups or c groups and
that's really designed around managing
the resources available to a container
so that things all the houses through
things like this container only gets 128
mega RAM or this container does not have
access to the network so you can you can
add and drop capabilities as needed
and that makes it sort of fairly
powerful to the old would have sort of
granularly control you know container in
much the same way you would do with sort
of point-and-shoot vmware interface to
say you know get this network interface
get this cpu core take this bit of
memory access to this file system create
a you know a virtual cd-rom drive
whatever it's a similar sort of level of
technology ok
in addition to files and processes can
also provide an isolated environment for
network addresses and ports so for
example I can have web servers running
in multiple containers all using port 80
by default the container does not expose
network ports to the outside but they
can be exposed manually or intentionally
which is a bit like opening up ports on
a firewall like IP tables right that's
correct so what happens is that what we
each container has its own network
interface and it's a virtual network
interface and you can run processes that
use network ports inside those
containers for example I can run 10
Apache containers all running on inside
port 80 on on the inside the container
and then outside the container I can say
expose this port and I can in if I want
to actually expose port 80 to port 80
but obviously I can only do that once
because you're in the map one can run
one port to inside the container to the
one port on the outside a host or by
default what doctor does is it says it
chooses a random high port and says I'm
going to do a network address
translation between this port 80 inside
the container and say port four nine 154
on the host and what I would then do is
for example I can have my multiple
Apaches processes running on different
ports and then I put a service discovery
tool or a load balancer or some sort of
proxy in front of it
HF proxy is very commonly used people
use things like nginx and service
discovery tools like zookeeper and and
etcb
and console essentially allow you to
sort of either proxy the connections or
provider way to say I want this
application query that particular
service discovery tool and say and it
says are that application is belongs to
these ten containers and you can choose
one of these ten ports which will
connect to the Apache process it's a
very flexible sort of scalable model
it's designed to be run there to run
complicated applications okay and docker
also has another facility to establish
links between containers so for example
I could have
a container with Apache in the front
apache running and then i could also
have my application server i don't know
a java application server and then
establish a link between them right
that's right so because because docker
is closed by default we know we think
the most secure way to do this is you
know you should be the one who decides
what ports to be exposed what you can do
is you can say that there are certain
types of containers for example a
database might for example or an
application server that should never be
exposed to the customer they should only
be exposed to the containers that
consume their resources so what I can do
is I can start that let's say that
database container and I can give it a
name I can call it like MySQL database 1
and then I can launch a say a web
container or a WordPress container or
something that Bou consumes something
from that database and I can tell it out
there on this docker host there's
another container called MySQL 1 what
you should do is you should choose a
link to that container which means I'll
create an encrypted tunnel between my
container and the target database
container on the specific port and then
I'll make the information available
inside the container so I actually we
create some DNS host entries and some
environment variables that an
application can consume to know about
where the database container is so
you're not the hard-coded IP addresses
or anything like that in there and then
what happens is that the database
container and the web container have now
have a link and they can only talk to
one another you can't you know that at
my school container you can you can ping
it or look at it on any one responder or
unless you are the web container in
which case it also ah
you're coming on on this port that means
you want to connect to the database and
get some information out so it's a very
simple way of constructing you know
application stacks and tiered
applications like that it's very basic
we call it about we call link version 1
and next release of the of the links
will have a much more dynamic concept so
they'll be you know they'll be over to
automatically update in the event of a
failure you know for example a know your
database container and one data center
fails therefore the red container with
automatic
default back to the second link which
may be a bad advice container another
data center or another container so
things like that are on the right path
for that which like that will make that
technology really interesting okay yeah
that's certainly what's the word I'm
looking for more convenient slightly
higher level than monkeying around with
specific IP addresses and specific ports
the idea is that really things people
you know what we we think doctor thinks
about the world in a very service
oriented architecture way and we're
heavily we're sort of deeply engaged
with sort of micro services you are the
world in the SLA view of the world which
is where you know you shouldn't have to
worry about things like IP addresses
importance you should be able to address
services should be able to say I know I
have a service out there called MySQL
that's what I want this application to
consume I want my infrastructure to take
care of that detail for me I shouldn't
have to go and ask someone to burn a
firewall rule or open a network pull it
up for change of being laying on it like
that might one my services should all be
able to talk to my other services with
appropriate controls and and appropriate
level availability right yeah that makes
perfect sense
by default the storage of container is
transient when the container goes away
the storage goes away doctor volumes
provide a mechanism for having
persistent storage and sharing between
containers can you explain so what
happens is that a container is a I
talked to before about those of
container images and and the layers
essentially when you run a container you
are creating a new layer on top that
that's the only read/write layer and
when you unless you do something to save
that information
it's a ephemeral it goes away when you
exit the container we had this concept
called volumes volumes are except
essentially another chunk of stand-alone
filesystem
I think about them a bit like a like a
mount point or something like that and I
what you can do is you can create a
container and make available parts of
that container as a volume example a
classic example might be
I run a an Apache container and I mount
as a volume the the bar dub-dub-dub
directory so that and the inside that I
have my my source code for my
application and I create that as a
volume I can either I can do two types
of ones ones I can mount from a from a
host file system example I can say I'm
running this container in the docker
host go up to this directory and mount
that directory inside my container which
allows me to have things like my source
code on a you know repository somewhere
and then run a container over the top of
it which means when I change my source
code I should be able to refresh the
container and see that that's updated
the second type of volume is one that
sort of I can share between containers
and the igloo example here might be I
have a database container I make the the
my SQL directory available as as a
volume I can then run another container
and mount that volume so I might example
I might people want to do replication or
I might want to be able to do backups or
capture logs or something like that so I
would run on my scroll container and
then run a backup container for example
that mounted the volume work containing
my MySQL directory database and then I
would be able to to do a backup of that
database save it somewhere and then exit
the container so it allows you to do
sort of it's a very much that sort of
multi tier sort of Multi multi stage
application and we very much focus on
containers being really doing one thing
like a container runs a web process or
it runs an application server or it does
backup so it does logging so maybe again
that sort of micro services services are
adapted to that style model we've been
talking about a container running from
an image and you touched on a little bit
in the introduction about building the
image up layer from light layer by layer
can you tell us a little bit more about
how we build images sure
so docker images are generally built for
what we call the docker file the docker
file is essentially a list of
instructions that are executed to build
the image
so every docket image starts from what
we call a base image and a base image is
what I talked about for it's that sort
of very thin skin of binaries and
libraries that that make something an
operating system so a base in which
might be something like Ubuntu and I
might be a particular version 1404 and
essentially what what that contains is
the bare minimum parts of the Ubuntu
operating system required to actually
run and interact with the kernel and do
basic things for example it contains you
know the live C and you know the apt-get
tool so you can do a package management
and then service management tools like
system B and stuff like that but it
doesn't contain things like X or or vir
more it just has the bare minimum
necessary in order to run an operating
system you think about like a like a
very stripped down skinny build and most
of those are you know 100 Meg couple
hundred Megan size which means compared
to a sort of virtual machine which is
probably multiple gigabytes in size then
you know they're very lightweight we
have our base image based on what the
busybox
distribution of Linux that's incredibly
small it's a matter of mega you know
tens might be 1024 megabytes or
something like that so you can imagine
you can run a whole lamp stack for
example on an operating system the 24
megabytes in size just pretty incredible
in terms of speed and Penna and capacity
what happens is we say that's on that
base image I might say from 1 to 1404 I
want to take some I wanted to have some
build steps and those steps might be
things like install Apache or might be
something like add some application code
or some configuration files inside the
image I then might configure some things
like I set the working directory inside
the image or the user at should Ronettes
and then perhaps I might want to
configure some networking I might want
to say you know this image should expose
if you choose to port 80 and then lastly
I tell the image when a container is run
from it
what's the default command I should run
and this might be for example I might in
the case of Apache I might say you know
run run the Apache daemon that's the
default thing you should do and then
when I run that docker build command
I rush I run that docker I run a command
called docker build which takes that
dock of the docker file execute sheets
instruction and at the end of it leaves
you what we call an image and the image
has an identifier like it's a long
shower like string and you can also give
it a name so I might call that image
Jane James Turnbull slash Apache which
is a very much like this sort of geek
view of the world I know there's a user
owner and then there's a name of what we
call it like essentially a repository
which is Apache I can then run a new
command called docker run and specify
the James Turnbull slash Apache image
and it'll launch an Apache web server
from that image if I want to make any
changes then I just update the docker
file we run docker build and as I said
it cases everything so it own it only
makes the changes you think are
necessary the images themselves can be
shared via docker hub or a company for
example with proprietary information
could run a repository internally is
that correct yeah so the the really
interesting thing and I talked to you
about portability about docker images is
is about very easy to ship around and we
have a software-as-a-service product
called docker hub which is very much
like github except it's for docker
images and we have a private version
which is also which is open source which
is kind of like github enterprise so
it's behind the firewall and sort of
typical workflow might be you know a
developer and a team of developers might
build an image for their application and
they would they would then they would
have the built image they've tested it
it works and they say them I want to
share this with the rest of the team so
they say docker push and the name of the
image and it pushes up to doctor docker
hub the docker hub also has private
repositories bit much like github does
so if you have you know if you want to
run you if you don't want to share that
with other people we can have a team of
people that have access to a private
repository it then says to the rest of
the team look there's a new version of
the docker docker image for our
application and the rest of the team go
docker Paul very much like the sort of
git workflow
they pull down the new version of the
image and because it's again
copy-on-write encased it'll only bring
down the changes necessary to update
your image to the latest version so it
doesn't move a lot of it doesn't take
very long doesn't move a lot of this
particular disk space doesn't take a lot
of time to update and then you know
everyone in the team is working off the
same image I mean that's pretty credible
because one of the classes problems with
development environments is that you
know as new people join the company they
get the development environment bilks or
refreshed or what happens to be but
ultimately there was some entropy there
and some some drift happens and you end
up with four or five people in the team
all of whom have quite different
development environments i when we when
Bill joined the team you know we had
this version of the JVM or he hasn't
updated the version of the gem slightly
but when Jane during the team a month
later you know we were using a different
version of the JVM or add an updated
while stack or whatever happened to be
in this case you avoid all those
problems because you know you can very
quickly and easily distribute the thing
where you no longer need to distribute a
whole new virtual machine or run a build
script or you know even pop you know I
know people who popped virtual machine
images onto USB keys and and and drag
them around people's offices that's are
horrified to find that people still do
that but it does happen you made the
comparison to get home if we say that
containers are like virtual machines
then docker hub gives us a way to share
enhance and use these virtual machines
like we do with source code on github
Pena's are really lightweight virtual
machines they are still there a
different type of virtual machine and
they rely on on that sort of more
operating system-level virtualization
but they are still type of virtual
machine and yes this the docker hub and
the whole docker tool is really designed
to allow you to accelerate the process
by which you can share that computer
resource Ike instead of having to wait
to spin up a virtual machine or bite for
a cloud instance or whatever happens to
be if you get sub second launch times
and incredibly fast build times
incredibly easy and cheap to distribute
that image around it takes away the pain
of a lot of the workflow that developers
have you don't have to go and ask her
ICS admin for
new machine I was talking to us he said
men at VMworld recently and I he said to
me I had a really big shock last month
the development team stopped asking me
for four new virtual machines and I said
I he said I didn't know what happened I
thought maybe they'd gone to Amazon or
something I thought I was gonna be in
trouble so I went to see them and asked
them what happened and they said do
remember we asked for that with a big
virtual machine last week and he said
yep
they said we stopped talking on it and
we bought a bunch of images for
applications and now we just have the
one virtual machine and we just request
containers from that and we build
containers from those images and we're
we're really happy we don't you know
surely that saved you some time to it
saved us a bunch of time you don't have
to provision things you don't have to
keep rebuilding images for us and
virtual machines and it at one is this
I've been realized that he was no longer
gonna have to do this stuff he was
thrilled because now the backlog of
things he actually wanted to do that
actually might deliver a real value now
what we're accessible to it and the
development team were thought it was
awesome they no longer had to log
tickets in a ticketing system to get
resources or wait for a virtual machine
or rebuild it or and worry about the
fact that the virtual machine they
requested wasn't the same as you know
may have deviated from production or
whatever happens to be and we think
that's an enormous amount of value to
deliver to app dev and operations teams
yeah that's a great example it explains
the value proposition for the developers
as well as the system admins docker
itself runs on a UNIX host because the
containers are using the layered file
system in the namespace and the other
the other things that you mentioned so
in theory a Macintosh or Windows machine
can't run docker but there's also the
boot to docker tool that provides the
ability effectively to do that
can you talk show so the moment doctors
very Lyn eccentric
I mean relies on Linux as Lunas kernel
and that's no no it's gonna be true I
will be I don't think I'm sharing too
many secrets when a few people are
publicly talked about the fact that it
would be relatively easy using things
like BSD Charles to make
Dokka our native citizen on Apple for
example or besties think technology like
Microsoft's drawbridge project and an
hyper-v it would be relatively the same
thing to have native containers on on
those platforms as well Windows
platforms but in the meantime whilst
that's still aspirational we do have a
talk with two docker Buddha docker is a
title recall I guess it's a micro
virtual machine it's a it's a it's a
it's basically an installer the docker
client and a tiny virtual machine that
runs the docker host that basically
comes with a very simple installer on
Windows and Mac that you can make the
download install and then run and what
happens is it from the from your command
line you can interact with that virtual
machine and we kind of fake out that the
so you know the the the fact that the
docker host is local there's a few
challenges with it still it's still not
it's still not you know that it's still
not seamless you know you are talking
about you have to create do some virtual
networking stuff that we configure most
of it for you but it doesn't it's not an
entirely native experience but it does
make it a lot easier to to use docker to
use blocker blocker locally on if you're
an apple or Windows centric shop okay
great
yeah that certainly opens up the use
cases for a lot of developers who aren't
on linux so that was a we did a little
bit of information about the nuts and
bolt of Dockers if listeners are
interested in getting more details I
highly recommend James's docker book
which will have link to in the show
notes let's kind of move up a little bit
and talk about how to use the darker
containers you talked about you touched
on this a bit docker run a docker
container runs one command and so that
would sort of suggest that a docker
container runs one service is there a
particular reason for that or you
mentioned service-oriented or
protectors and micro-services I suppose
I'm asking is there a technical reason
or was it kind of a philosophical reason
just that you think the micro services
and soas
are the way that development should be
going and there's not really a technical
reason you decides a philosophical
there's nothing stopping you or any
mortal processes in the doc container
and you can use a service management
tool like system D or supervisor or
something like that to say you could run
your entire lamp stack in a single tiny
could run you know Apache and MySQL and
PHP and WordPress all that stuff inside
a docker container our view of the world
though is that applications are getting
more and more complex and their
relationships you know become more more
complex as a results you know open ports
and you know different bits of access
control and configuration and
integration and over asked you use
large-scale infrastructure problems that
I've seen have largely been caused by
the fact that people don't understand
how their applications interact interact
and the particular large enterprises
they're often people who have developed
the original application no longer work
and the company there's a bunch of
inherited knowledge or some some dated
documentation and a significant part of
the debugging of a problem can just be
identifying how the application now
works now and took together I think in
that SOA microservices world where you
can say okay I have ten containers that
make up my application I have a way to
introspect those containers and see how
they link together we talked about
linking the containers and we talked
about what ports were open I can
introspect all of that with
programmatically if I want to and say I
have these ten containers that have
these ports open that I hook to those
other ports these containers contain
this turn that link together in this way
I understand how the fundamentals of the
architectural application works this
container is the one that's causing the
problem
maybe if I fix that the rest of the
things will fall into place I think that
sort of debugging experience is far
simpler and I'm speaking largely someone
who the last few years have been
focusing on solving operational problems
but you know I also think that that in
terms of building applications in terms
of mocking and testing applications and
in terms of you know I guess allowing
other people to integrate with your
applications that very service oriented
architecture view of the world makes a
lot of that much simpler and I think
there are some extreme examples I mean
Amazon's the classic example here where
every Amazon application development
group are basically publishing API spec
and everything everything internal to
inside of that spec is kind of a black
box to all of the other application
developer groups and they just interact
using you know chrome is a published API
spec you for you write your service
against our API you know that we we go
in to make some guarantees them to work
that's probably a bit extreme but I
think that my view of the world is that
a lot of services and applications would
be would be far better constructed and
far easier to manage and far easy to
build and test
I think they if they more drifted
towards that we have a specification an
API or a service or a data format or a
polar buffer for what happens to be and
we publish that and other people consume
it and that's sort of somewhat what's
driven docker and think about that and
other aspects include things like the
fact that we did come from a we built a
platform as a service product called
cloud before we pivoted to focus on
docker so a lot of our sort of DNA is
very much platform as a service and
platform of services obviously again
very service II sort of oriented it if
I've got an application and I've broken
it into separate services and I'm
putting each service in its own
container how am I gonna start them all
and you know you know connect them I
guess we use the links to connect my
application server to my database but
how do I start them all and deal with
the dependencies like the database has
to be running before the application and
things like that
sure so there's um this is an area
that's sort of developing really quickly
you have to run the docker is just over
a year old at this point about a year
and a half I think so you know it's a
toddler by the standards of a low
technology and
sort of you know with the initial focus
of decor is really on that sort of
compute unit sort of stuff and the next
stage of stuff that we're looking at
right now is more that orchestration
story which is now she said the classic
example is you know I want to start a
web service but it relies on the
database starting and then obviously you
know that's the simplest example it
makes it more complex of example if it's
multiple database backends across
multiple geographies or multiple
application tiers or whatever happens to
be so we've found we recently acquired a
tool in the docker ecosystem called fig
and fig is an orchestration tool allows
you to define collections of containers
so it says now our service is made up of
this container this container in this
container or an application is made up
of this code and run them in this
sequence and link them together so that
starts to solve some of those problems
and there's a huge ecosystem of tools
appearing up as a result of this an
including integration with things like
you know zookeeper and and other sort of
service discovery related tools and we
think that our you know whilst Dockers
as sort of you know did the real the
real sort of exciting part of the next
sort of wave of docker will be building
those sort of orchestration and
management tools cost to manage than all
that sort of stuff and so those are
going to be aimed at running containers
on multiple hosts as well because so far
we've been talking about kind of doctor
in the small on a single host right yeah
so we launched a tool prototype court
called mid swarm i'm swarm like a swarm
of wasps my accent always defeats that
word but that tool was really designed
to sort of prototype how you would get
docker host to talk to one another it's
currently no containers on one docker
host have to use the network to talk to
one another
but really they should have a
back-channel communication you should
essentially be able to have you know doc
I was communicating together and we sort
of look at this sort of like a chatty
kind of way to say whether docker host
and I run Apache web services and
another dog host saying oh I have a
database back-end that needs an Apache
front-end can you can you link one of
your containers is one of my content and
that starts to create
really awesome stories around
scalability order scaling redundancy and
you start to sort of be able to build
really complex applications which sharp
until now has been very challenging for
lot of organizations how does darker fit
into the immutable infrastructure
movement in DevOps does docker replace
or compete with tools like chef and
puppet I don't think I think it's
complementary rather than a sort of no I
think you're probably gonna be running
well let me start with you so the
immutable infrastructure there's really
stateless application so you actually
build our you build a a unit of compute
in this case a container
it contains the source code everything
and there's no there's no data to update
there's no database to know it's
essentially a it's essentially a closed
system and it's very common in in sort
of high-performance computing it's very
common in sort of pharmaceutical and
scientific computing and it's become
very common in sort of web operation
shops because you know in this case you
don't want to a lot of your problems
as I said exist because entropy happens
and drift happens in configuration and
and a host becomes different in this
case you know host always say the same
you want to recreate the host you can
delete the host and recreate a new one
and be guaranteed to get back to that
for the last known good state so popular
chef and ansible and salt all exists to
manage that entropy that drift
configuration drift so we look at we
look at docker as you know you are
probably be running less of those
because your containers are probably
much more short-lived or they're
immutable and it's much cheaper instead
of using popular chef to rebuild a
container back to a known wood state you
would just might use them to kill the
container and we start a new one with a
partner and chef is sort of
complementary is that the dock I always
need to be provisioned and managed
that's still an operating system sort of
task they've done ostraka images need to
be built and inside your puppet modules
and your chef cookbooks you probably
have a bunch of useful information about
how up ok
are built so you can actually build your
docker images using popular chef and
then you can when you deploy them in
docker you know you know we're going to
do the part of maintaining them of
ongoing basis you just dispose of them
and recreate them when you need to okay
yeah I can definitely see kind of the
the complementary aspect there I've
heard an analogy between docker
containers and the shipping containers
that are used for intermodal
transportation across ships and trains
and trucks can you explain that a bit so
this is analogy obviously docker docks
containers you know we we weren't
stretching too far when we when we
basically stole a bunch of language and
and and terminology from that industry
but the really interesting story behind
I actually didn't know this story before
I started working at docker but um
so prior to intermodal shipping
containers which are you know the big
steel containers you're familiar with
that you know go on cargo ships pretty
much what happened was there was a verse
or purse or a quartermaster over ship
and they based the job was to take all
of the goods you need to ship and pack
them on the ship in Satellite of the
ship wooden capsized and you didn't
stink stick for gunpowder next to the
matches now all that sort of stuff was
was you know the appropriate weights and
measures immune instigating that was
gonna spill next to your precious
carpets or your or your expensive spices
and it made the process of loading and
unloading ships really quite cumbersome
and it often took days to to carefully
pack a ship and it meant that you know
if something went wrong on the journey
for example we oughta got into something
and there was a good chance you would
lose part of your cargo and it added
considerable overhead to the shipping
process
intermodal shipping containers came
along and attentive someone said how
about we build steel boxes then all
identical all have the same hooks and
harnesses and fittings all have the same
labeling have a consistent system of of
identification and then it doesn't
matter what we pack inside them because
they're all isolated from one another
and they're incredibly portable you can
lift them off a ship and put them on a
truck you don't even have to open the
container as part of the process it's
all very seamless so we thought when we
were building docker that
this is actually a really apt analogy so
we don't really care what you put inside
the container you know we don't really
really care about how you build the
thing inside the container you can you
can stuff in you know ten web web
servers or one big database or or you
know a single service whatever you want
inside the container or what we provide
to you is a way to move that container
around through its image and a way
operations people to have the same hooks
and and leavers and identification and
all our stuff on the outside so that
really the application developer cares
about the thing that's that the payload
inside the container and the operations
person cares about managing the
container it's actually the transport
and the crane the deal off the graph the
ship with the crane and putting on the
truck instead and hence that that
analogy really resonated with us and
it's not it's not perfect it would argue
that we've greatly simplified the
history of intermodal shipping but you
know it is a marketing analogy not a um
no we're not we're not trying to sell a
deep philosophical story but still the
end result is is very similar you talked
about the tremendous streamlining of
intermodal goods as they're being loaded
and unloaded from ships or trucks or
trains and you know you've given us a
couple of examples of the streamlining
of these virtual machines or containers
and how that just accelerates
development and operation yeah one thing
I didn't throw in there was that after
intermodal shipping containers were
introduced
shipping time is reduced by 70% and the
cost of shipping something I don't know
I'm I'm I'm in my 40s i it's pretty
predates me but my parents remember sort
of the idea of shipping something
substantial for a consumer from say
where I grew up in Australia to the UK
no that was a non-trivial quite
expensive exercise and you could spend
six to eight weeks waiting for a bag to
get from London to to Sydney
you know the process of intermodal
shipping containers basically massively
accelerated commerce and and shipping
across across the world
and basically change the way people do
business and it
the walls we have described as the
market analogy but no we think there is
the potential to make that sort of
fundamental difference in the way people
operationally and lobular build
applications operationally manage them
and we get through this sort of for many
workloads a sort of next wave of
computer it's a pretty tall order to
deliver this the same orders of
magnitude of improvement but good luck I
think I think that the challenges
obviously there but um and it's a
challenging problem I think people need
to remember how short the history is of
so virtual machines are relatively new
technology themselves and really the
first people to monetize them was really
but wasn't really been where and that's
about 10 to 11 years old so now as a
technology they were relatively recent
and uh you know obviously the the
virtual machines radically change the
way people you know were able to do with
infrastructure and they basically
enabled the cloud without virtual
machines probably the cloud or bunch of
that stuff wouldn't exist and that
happened in a relatively short period of
time and the concepts we look at now as
going sort of as being sort of par for
the course like you know having your ESX
server and running 100 virtual machines
we really were technological marvels
that you know 20 years ago and I started
in the mainframe world where there was
things that logical partitioning but
that was like a million dollar point of
entry you know I think they give us X
away now so I think you know we've seen
some amazing changes in in sort of the
infrastructure management in the last
and 10 20 years I'm hoping docker will
represent next wave of that that sort of
change in in the next sort of five or
six years in the turn right sure sure
them that makes perfect sense
do you see darker in containers
replacing traditional hardware
virtualization I think for certain
workloads you know interesting we are
you know someone today that I think that
platform as a service and infrastructure
as a service so those sort of OpenStack
and Cloud Foundry and Amazon's of
the virtual machine is an action ideal
resource for for compute it's quite
heavy weight and it is um he adds a
significant amount of edge to those
companies platforms so I think for
certain types of workloads like that
that container makes a lot more sense
you mentioned immutable infrastructure
high performance computing those sort of
workloads know our natural fit right now
for docker anyone doing micro services
or service honored architectures service
buses anything like that
I think blocker is again an ideal use
case that's strongly recommend people
look at it it naturally forces you to
think about your architecture in that in
the quite healthy way obviously there
are going to be physical servers or
particular workloads or legacy workloads
that you can't move into that sort of
architecture I certainly wouldn't go
into a company if they've got a massive
brownfields COBOL application and say
you know we can replace this with docker
containers and that that's that's not
realistic and certainly it's very Linux
centric right now but I think for a wide
variety of workloads particularly in the
dev test role where you are thinking
about that continuous integration and we
worried about collaboration and
cooperation and speed to market gain
that code from a developer into a
production environment if those are key
concerns for you then I would almost
certainly say that docker is an
attractive fit there are a lot of tools
in and around docker we've already kind
of touched on a couple of them you
mentioned fig there's core LS Panamax
means us many many of them why do you
suppose docker seemed so hot right now
this being the the summer of nineteen of
2014 and why is it attracting so much
activity so you know you talk to beta
for about SLAR zones and base details
and Dockers prerunner in the linux world
was Alexei containers so Linux
containers they're called and we
originally based some of our ideas on
that technology I think the big
challenge has been that all of those
bits of technology we're not actual that
easy to use
two roots Solaris zones
you know actually containers all
required a reasonably savvy sis admin or
a reasonably savvy engineer to developed
or work with well one of the first
things we sat down when we looked at
docker was was basically we said this
needs to be a workflow that a developer
who doesn't know anything about
infrastructure should be able to use and
so our you know every time we build
something we flip back to the does this
add complexity that would prevent a you
know as a front-end engineer who knows
nothing about virtual machines or
virtualizations there's no idea what
what the stack is application runs on is
and we'll be able to use this tool so
that's been our focus and that's I think
has driven a significant amount of
adoption the fact that developers can
learn to use docker in a very short
period of time and require them to know
nothing about the Linux kernel nothing
about how namespaces in C groups work
nothing about infrastructure some very
basic command line stuff and some very
basic networking stuff but you know you
know like this is a port and and this
Court is not clear that's other port I
mean really simplistic stuff developers
have gone nuts over and they're
basically gone this is really easy to
use and I cited the example before of
not having to talk to us he said min
about getting a resource that's a big
thing for developers right you know you
you're like I I knew I need a copy of
the test the production database created
on a VM in the test environment I'll
open a ticket and then or maybe I'll put
in my thumbs for two weeks and that's
not because suicide means a crap it's
because you know they aren't they are
responding to a thousand tickets like
that as well as trying to keep the
production services up so you know this
is something that that helps reduce that
they're horrible friction and they're
horrible sort of interaction as a result
developers have just loved it and
operations people to you know that they
look at the attractive sort of hyper
scale nature of it some of them have
very big invoices from companies like
VMware when they buy a lot of virtual
machine licenses
something that helps cut that bill a
little bit or make things more
manageable or reduces the friction
between them and developers where they
you know have an outage and the
developer says well it works on my
machine that a production person goes
but it doesn't work in production where
the customers are you know I've been in
operations and engineering for 25 years
and I can I've run out of fingers and
toes to count those conversations I've
had often at 4 o'clock in the morning
where some developers throws his hands
up and says it worked for me when I
built it now what's your problem you're
an idiot and and those interactions are
unfortunately in common and not pleasant
if you're going to reduce you know not
one a month of those away that's an
worth an enormous amount of money in
terms of uptime and morale and
collaboration and a bunch of other
things so for me there's a I find that
really exciting sure and not to man
mention the fact that if you're not
having those discussions or debates or
battles it's all the more cycles
everyone has for advancing the
enterprise that you're in what's in
store for the future of docker you kind
of touched on some hints of what might
be coming yeah so I think for us docker
hub product you know we're working
really hard to make that to make that
much more features in you know it now
has been authentication it has the
concept of organizations and teams and
private repositories that allows it to
be sort of used in a very similar way to
people use github which is known instead
it hooks into github and bit back and a
bunch of those things you can have your
source code there and your docker images
hooked in so when you make a change to
your source code on github new docker
hub images are automatically updated so
that's a pretty cool sort of bit of
technology we look to expand that we're
also going to look to take that we have
an open source product that as part of
that functionality where we want to make
the actual full docker hub product to be
on-premise and probably early next year
we'll have an on-premise product
offering the wall are those people that
aren't comfortable about sending their
private data out of the firewall they
can they can manage it all internally
very much like the github enterprise
product and on the dock or product
itself um it's really about moving up
the value chain and you know currently
we're good at managing no small groups
of containers on a single docker host we
want to be able to manage complex
applications across multiple hosts most
hosting
multiple locations and really that the
technology we're building around that is
is sort of focused on me I want to make
that really easy for people again with
this is something that a developer the
developer should be able to build a
simple stack you know themselves without
needing to engage with lots of other
people but operations people know should
be have that have access to all of the
bells and whistles underneath and that's
really been our sort of development sort
of our mantra
something we I don't think we you just
mentioned but I certainly didn't mention
explicitly is the fact that docker is an
open-source tool and it's free for
anyone to use
docker is also the company behind the
docker project what is the business
model for the company are there some
specific some specific area of the
ecosystem or the landscape that docker
is targeting or carving out for itself
yeah so the doctor companies really
exist for two reasons one is that we
provide a lot of the governance around
the doc project we're a reasonably large
contributor to the open source project
ourselves and so on and I access CTO is
sort of the benevolent dictator of that
project operates a bit like Linus
Torvalds without all the swearing and
our business model is structured around
building that that open source tool that
we're gonna make learning in a couple of
things one is the docker hub product the
private repositories I mentioned that
there there there you have to pay for
those very much like you have to pay for
private repositories on github and add
some more services for pay services on
top of that that we think that are will
be attractive to a lot of people we also
sell services and training around open
sourced docker they're really designed
to be able to help you get started with
docker for example you know we offer
public today public training course we
offer on-site training courses we offer
services people who can help you get
started localizing some proof of concept
and then we offer support so if you have
problems you can call us and ask
questions but then in future I talked
about we can build some more products at
the ready chain we think people will
actually pay for those products okay I
think that that um one of the things
that has been missing not just in the
container orb and the more broadly is
really powerful orchestration tools and
really powerful service management tools
no I think those things have been
inaccessible to the average hunter or
you know they'll be the cost lots and
lots of money
you know the BMC or to valise of the
world HP openview and things like that
or even the VMware products in a
reasonably priced C or they've required
no strong engineering talent measures
for example a zookeeper really awesome
tools but they require pretty mature
engineering practices and pretty you
know pretty strong engineers are able to
sort of they're not off the shelf tools
you have to adapt them to your
environment so we think if we build some
really powerful orchestration and
management tools focused around docker
but hopefully able to also integrate and
manage with other tools that people will
want to pay money for those so as we
wind things down here are there any
items I didn't cover that you think our
listeners would like to know about I
think that was on week I would a bit of
everything I hope I hope I was a
articulate enough to encourage people to
give docker a try but on I think we kept
it open you off sure well in terms of
giving doctor a try where can people
find out more about docker and follow
you sure so website is
www.antakungfu.com it ation how to
install docker and how to get started
I also had a book called The Joker book
which is available at www.cerritos.edu
build from scratch to complex things and
I go from you know no knowledge of
docker to install in docker building
docker images very basic dock
operational tasks are wired up to sort
of complex service discovery introduced
things like feegan console and stuff
like that as well as extending doctor
yourself and integrating with the docker
api so that's been available since
Finster
and it's very cheap I think it's about
$9.99 it's like that might even be cheap
on Amazon and it's an old for my set you
can find me on twitter my twitter handle
is kar ta r and it's awesome website k
RT on it has a bunch of blog posts
including some about docker and some
other topics interest me okay great
we'll include links to all of these
items in the show notes James thanks for
being on the show jobs thanks very much
for having me was back fun sure
this is Charles Anderson for software
engineering radio thank you for
listening thanks for listening to se
radio an educational program brought to
you by I Triple E software magazine for
more information about the podcast
including other episodes visit our
website at se - radio net to support us
you can advertise su radio by clicking
the Digg reddit delicious or slide
buttons on the site or by talking about
us on Facebook Twitter or your own blog
if you have feedback specific to an
episode please use the commenting
feature on the site so that other
listeners can respond to your comments
as well this and all of the episodes of
se radio is licensed under the creative
commons two-point-five license please
see the website for details thanks again
for your support
[Music]
me